{"tossups": [{"question": "At this site in 2007, Fendi staged a widely-publicized fashion show. <em>Simitai</em> is a \u201cwild\u201d or \u201cunrestored\u201d section of this site. Mutianyu and Badaling are two of the most-visited parts of this site. Parts of this site date back to the Warring States Period, and Qin Shi Huang ordered the construction and unification of other parts of this site, though it was ineffectual at stopping large invading armies such as the Mongols. For the point, name this defensive barrier north of Beijing.", "answer": "<b><u>Great Wall</u></b> of <b><u>China</u></b> (or <b><u>Wanli Changcheng</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This god is sometimes referred to as the White Tezcatlipoca, the god of light and the ruler of the western cardinal direction. In one version of a myth often compared to the story of Jesus Christ, this god was born to a virgin named Chimalman, to whom the god Onteol appeared in a dream. In Mayan culture, this god had two equivalents: Gukumatz and Kukulkan, whose names also roughly translate to \u201cfeathered serpent.\u201d For the point, name this Aztec god of the wind.", "answer": "<b><u>Quetzalcoatl</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The Ishmaelites, a subset of this group, all held the last name Hajaly and were supposedly extinguished by King Coloman of Hungary during 13th century inquisitions. An attack orchestrated by this group nearly ended the life of King Edward I of England after he came into contact with a poison dagger. The polymath Silvestre de Sacy was the first European to connect this organization\u2019s name to those who smoke the drug \u201chashish.\u201d For the point, name this order of Ismailis who served as contract killers in the Medieval Arabic world.", "answer": "Order of <b><u>Assassins</u></b> (or <b><u>Hashshashin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the 14th century, mathematicians at the Kerala School explored principles, including the Taylor series and infinite series approximations, that would one day become crucial to this mathematical study. In 1672, Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz concluded the tangent to be a ratio between ordinates and abscissas, discovering the fundamental principles of this mathematical study independently of Sir Isaac Newton. For the point, name this mathematical study of continuous change.", "answer": "Infinitesimal <b><u>Calculus</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "This writer championed a return of European colonialism in places like Congo and Uganda in a 1990s article while at the <em>Daily Telegraph</em>. While foreign secretary, this man compared the damage he saw in Anguilla and Barbados from Hurricane Irma to the aftermath of the bombing of Hiroshima. European Council President Donald Tusk nicknamed this politician \u201cMr. No Deal\u201d due to his inability to sign a trade deal prior to leaving the EU. For the point, name this Prime Minister of the UK, a Conservative who once served as Mayor of London.", "answer": "Boris <b><u>Johnson</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This non-American city's Ohel Moshe Synagogue was part of a ghetto for Jewish refugees. This city was to be rebuilt into a 1927 grid plan with its core shaped like the character for \"center.\" This city had a Communist purge in the April 12 Incident, and in this city, Huang Jinrong operated the Green Gang. For decades, this city's Huangpu Park banned Chinese people from entering. This city's <em>Waitan</em>, or \"The Bund,\" features stylized European architecture like the HSBC Building. Located on the Yangtze delta, for the point, name this most populous Chinese city.", "answer": "<b><u>Shanghai</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One of these events in 1979 was cancelled after an explosion set off by DJ Steve Dahl. At one of these events, a Columbia grad called himself \"the luckiest man on the face of the Earth.\" In 1919, Buck Weaver and seven associates were accused of throwing a series of these events to fulfill a bet made by Arnold Rothstein. For the point, examples of what type of event have included a tumultuous Disco Demolition Night, the Farewell Speech of Lou Gehrig, and the misplays of the infamous Black Sox?", "answer": "<b><u>Baseball game</u></b>s (do not accept or prompt on \u201cWorld Series\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Stylized as a Platonic dialogue, Antonio Rocco anonymously published a novel titled for this man which is considered the first LGBT novel. Pericles served as the guardian of this military figure as a child, and this man successfully captured Byzantium after his reinstatement as a general fighting for the Delian League. Earlier, this man lost favor after advocating for the disastrous Sicilian Expedition, fleeing his homeland for its rival Sparta.  For the point, name this 5th century BC Athenian general during the Peloponnesian War.", "answer": "<b><u>Alcibiades</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The Kakheti kingdom revolted against this empire led by its ruler Teimuraz I during the Bakhtrioni uprising. Petrus de Monte Libano acted as a courier between this empire and the Habsburgs in an attempt to weaken Suleiman the Magnificent through coordinated warfare. This empire that mass converted from Sunni to Shia was first led by Ismail I, who temporarily lost their capital of Isfahan. For the point, name this gunpowder empire led by a Shah in early modern Persia.", "answer": "<b><u>Safavid</u></b> Empire (accept <b><u>Safavid</u></b> Persia; accept <b><u>Safavid</u></b> Iran)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During World War Two, the British recruited men of this predominantly Muslim ethnic group into the local \"V Force\" to fight against the pro-Japanese Rakhines. Shortly thereafter, members of this ethnic group attempted to merge Arakan with East Pakistan. A 1982 citizenship law enacted by the Burmese military junta caused much of this ethnic group to become stateless. For the point, name this minority ethnic group of Myanmar, whose genocide resulted in the largest human exodus in Asia since the Vietnam War.", "answer": "<b><u>Rohingya</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was mentored by Otilio Monta\u00f1o S\u00e1nchez, who became acquainted with this man's cousin Amador Salazar. This man authored a document that includes a declaration from the Junta of the State of Morelos and denounces a rival's Plan de San Luis Potos\u00ed. This author of the Plan of Ayala led the Liberation Army of the South at the Battle of Cuautla, at which he defeated the Federal Army of Porfirio D\u00edaz. For the point, name this agrarian revolutionary who lends his name to a far-left guerrilla force in Chiapas, Mexico.", "answer": "Emiliano <b><u>Zapata</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Underwater bridges suggested by this man proved vital in transporting machinery while fighting the Kwantung Army at the Battle of Khalkhin Gol. The failure of Operation Citadel and the Nazi\u2019s inability to envelop the Kursk salient has been attributed to this general, who reinforced the city with anti-tank artillery. Aleksandr Vasilevsky and this man planned Operation Uranus, during which the Red Army defeated the German Sixth Army in Stalingrad. For the point, name this Communist Party Minister of Defense and prominent Soviet general during World War Two.", "answer": "Georgy <b><u>Zhukov</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1954, the Bingtuan, or XPCC, was founded in this region to invigorate the local economy and strengthen the border with the Soviet Union. More recently, this region became the site of the East Turkestan independence movement, considered by the People\u2019s Republic of China to be a terrorist organization. Since 2017, Chinese authorities in this region have damaged or destroyed over 16,000 mosques. For the point, name this Chinese autonomous region, the focus of human rights groups for the imprisonment of Uyghur [[WEE-gur]] Muslims.", "answer": "<b><u>Xinjiang</u></b> Uyghur Autonomous Region (or <b><u>Xinjiang</u></b> Province; accept <b><u>Sinkiang</u></b>, prompt on \"XUAR\"; do not accept \"Uyghurstan\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This piece was written while its creator was serving as the temporary director of an American conservatory, and its third movement was inspired by <em>The Song of Hiawatha</em>. The song <em>Goin\u2019 Home</em> was later adapted from an English horn solo in this piece\u2019s Largo second movement. Harry Burleigh introduced the Czech composer of this symphony to African-American spirituals. For the point, name this final Antonin Dvorak symphony whose nickname reflects the source of its inspiration.", "answer": "<em><b><u>New World</u></b> Symphony</em> (accept From the <b><u>New World</u></b>; prompt on Dvorak\u2019s \"Ninth\" Symphony)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Juan Guzm\u00e1n Tapia investigated this man\u2019s regime and the disappearance of American journalist Charles Horman, finally placing this man under house arrest in 2001. This man, who enlisted the \u201cChicago Boys,\" used the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency to amass a fortune hidden in the Riggs Bank. Upon being surrounded by this man\u2019s forces, the sitting president, Salvador Allende died in the presidential Moneda Palace in Santiago. For the point, name this US-backed Chilean dictator.", "answer": "Augusto <b><u>Pinochet</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "It\u2019s not Turkey, but Janissaries originally from this modern-day nation led by Patrona Halil captured Istanbul and appointed common folk to positions of nobility. In the north of this modern nation, the Christian noble Skanderbeg led a twenty-year revolt against the Ottomans. In 1967, this nation was proclaimed the world's first atheist state by the bunker-building First Secretary, Enver Hoxha [[HODGE-uh]]. For the point, name this Balkan nation with capital at Tirana.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Albania</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Cetshwayo kaMpande successfully deployed this military force against British expeditionary forces at the Battle of Isandlwana. Mthethwa chieftain Dingiswayo reformed this force, basing its ranking on the <em>iNtanga</em> age hierarchy. This military unit that wielded the <em>Iklwa</em> stabbing spear often used the \u201cHorn of the Buffalo\u201d formation to encircle and pin their enemies. For the point, name this Zulu word for \u201cRegiment,\u201d a force used by Shaka to conquer much of Southern Africa.", "answer": "<b><u>Impi</u></b> (prompt on \"Zulu\" army and similar answers before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1991, the Dmanisi archaeological site in this region made history by yielding the five oldest hominid specimens ever discovered outside the African continent. The Greek hero, Jason, is said to have met Medea, whose father was the king of Colchis, in this region, and Ovid described this region as comprising the westernmost area of Scythia. In 1829, Khillar Khachirov first ascended the eastern summit of Mount Elbrus, this region\u2019s highest mountain. For the point, name this region, home to the countries of Georgia and Azerbaijan.", "answer": "<b><u>Caucasus</u></b> (or <b><u>Caucasia</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This company drastically changed its operations based on research by geologist Walter K. Link, and in 1963, this company opened its Cenpes research center. Marcelo Odebrecht was convicted of active corruption for his role in a scandal involving this company, which also involved politician Eduardo Cunha. S\u00e9rgio Moro led an investigation into this company, which accused figures like Lula da Silva and Dilma Rousseff of kickbacks and corruption. Operation Car Wash investigated, for the point, what state-owned Brazilian petroleum company?", "answer": "<b><u>Petrobras</u></b> (or <b><u>Petr\u00f3leo Brasileiro</u></b> S.A.; prompt on \"Brazilian Petroleum Company\" and similar answers)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "For this country, World War One didn\u2019t end until 1958, as it was not a party to the Treaty of Versailles, though its citizens had long since returned from fighting as part of the French Legions. In 1934, Boris Skossyreff declared himself Boris I, king of this country and attempted reforms through a self-published national constitution. Two weeks later, this country\u2019s co-prince, Justi Guitart i Vilardebo, expelled him. For the point, name this microstate landlocked between France and Spain.", "answer": "Principality of <b><u>Andorra</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person acted in the play <em>The Defeat of the Aggressors</em> about the Suez Crisis after being repatriated to one nation to work as a hotel attendant. This man briefly returned to power in 1917 through the warlord Zhang Xun [[ZHONG SHUN]], who had previously served in the guard of this man\u2019s relative, the Empress Dowager Cixi [[SEE-SHEE]]. As a child, this man was overthrown in the Xinhai [[SHIN-HIGH]] Revolution and later led the puppet government of Manchukuo. For the point, name this last emperor of the Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty of China.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Puyi</u></b> (accept <b><u>Xuantong</u></b> Emperor)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Norwegian creator of this 1893 work made several versions in oil paint and pastel as well as a lithograph. One expert has suggested that the main figure in this work was inspired by a Peruvian mummy. Some scholars cite the continued effects of the eruption of Krakatoa over the skies of Western Europe, including Norway, for the color of this work\u2019s reddish sky. Ftp, what famous artwork by Edvard Munch [[MOONK]] depicts an open-mouthed figure on a bridge?", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Scream</u></b> of Nature</em> (accept <em><b><u>Der Schrei</u></b> der Natur</em>; accept <em><b><u>Skrik</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A man with this surname recaptured Fort Sackville in the Battle of Vincennes, a year after capturing Kaskaskia without firing any weapons. That man with this surname was nicknamed \"Conqueror of the Old Northwest.\u201d A man with this surname was the younger of a pair of men who stayed at Fort Mandan while accompanied by a child named Pompey. That man with this surname hired Toussaint Charbonneau and his Shosone wife, Sacagawea. For the point, name this shared surname of George and William, who mapped the Louisiana Territory with Merriweather Lewis.", "answer": "<b><u>Clark</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This dictator\u2019s \u201cMinistry of Justice\u201d perpetuated state-sanctioned kidnappings of the <em>ni\u00f1os perdidos</em> after a chaotic civil war. This dictator held onto the <em>Plaza de Soberania</em>, including the cities of Ceuta and Melilla, after the independence of Morocco. This man brought back one nation\u2019s title of Kingdom in 1947, crowning the Infante Juan Carlos as the figurehead royal, and he defeated the Republicans in a 1930s conflict with support from Italy and Nazi Germany. For the point, name this Falangist leader of Spain.", "answer": "Francisco <b><u>Franco</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Ishaq I of this empire deployed 2,000 camel mounted soldiers after Ahmad al-Araj requested the cession of the Taghaza salt mines. The <em>Tarikh al-Sudan</em> records that this empire\u2019s ruler, Askia the Great, undertook the Air Mountain Campaign and revived Islamic scholarship in Timbuktu. This empire\u2019s forces deployed cattle against Judar Pasha, which then turned around and stampeded this empire's own soldiers during the Battle of Tondibi. For the point, name this African empire with capital at Gao [[GOW]] which absorbed the Mali Empire in the 16th century.", "answer": "<b><u>Songhai</u></b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this country, texts like \"Expositions of the Religion\" were written in the only known Germanic language to use Arabic script. In the 1970s, this country's government isolated many speakers of its Venda language. Miriam Makeba was one of the first musicians to record music in this country's Xhosa language. An official language of this country developed from the mixture of a Dutch pidgin called Hottentot and Cape Dutch. For the point, name this country, whose eleven official languages include Zulu and Afrikaans.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>South Africa</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A follow-up to this case used a phrase from Francis Thompson's poem, \"The Hound of Heaven.\" After 25 years, this case was reopened by Richard Jones and Charles Scott, Jr. Philip Elman claimed credit for the ruling in this case, and, as a clerk, William Rehnquist wrote a \"random thought\" on this case, decrying its outcome. This case involved the option of sending a child to either Monroe or Sumner Elementary. Earl Warren led a 9-0 decision ending desegregation of schools in, for the point, what 1954 Supreme Court case?", "answer": "<em>Oliver</em> <em><b><u>Brown</u></b> et al. v. Board of Education of Topeka, et al.</em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After Lady Anne spits on him, this \u201crudely stamp'd\u201d villain still manages to seduce her. In the first scene of the play named for him, this future king shares his nefarious plans in a soliloquy, before setting in motion a chain of events that will lead to his coronation and eventual death in battle. For the point, name this Shakespearean villain whose first line is, \u201cNow is the winter of our discontent made glorious summer by this sun of York,\" historically killed at the Battle of Bosworth Field.", "answer": "<b><u>Richard III</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "A man with this position, Agostino Depretis, mastered the process of building centrist governments known as <em>Trasformismo</em>. Beginning the chaotic \u201cYears of Lead,\u201d the <em>Brigate Rosse</em> [[bree-GAH-tay ROH-say]] kidnapped and executed a man with this position, Aldo Moro. The nation this position serves supposedly secured a \u201cMutilated Victory\u201d after not having its demands of Dalmatian territory met by the Allies, leading to the resignation of a man with this position, Vittorio Orlando. For the point, name this position held by Silvio Burlesconi and Benito Mussolini.", "answer": "<b><u>Prime Minister</u></b> of the Republic of <b><u>Italy</u></b> (accept <b><u>PM</u></b> in place of <b><u>Prime Minister</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This leader willingly ceded the uninhabited island of Katchatheevu to the government of Sirimavo Bandaranaike as a gesture of goodwill. In part to assist her son, Sanjay, this political leader nationalized the automobile company Maruti Udyog, later merging it with Suzuki. Due to Operation Blue Star and the Indian Army\u2019s violent action in Amritsar, this woman\u2019s Sikh bodyguards assassinated her. For the point, name this daughter of Jawaharlal Nehru who served as Prime Minister of India throughout much of the 1970s and 1980s.", "answer": "<b><u>I</u></b>ndira <b><u>Gandhi</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s assassination coincided with the climax of the Naguib Mahfouz novel <em>The</em> <em>Day the Leader was Killed</em>. This political figure coordinated with Hafez al-Assad on an invasion of Israel that occurred on Yom Kippur. This president occupied the Sinai Peninsula after the Israeli withdrawal, and he was a close ally of Gamal Abdal Nasser during the Free Officers Movement that overthrew King Farouk. For the point, name this Egyptian president who won a Nobel Peace Prize with Menachim Begin.", "answer": "Anwar el-<b><u>Sadat</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}